Finding Aid for Frank R. Brown papers, 1980-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank R. Brown papers 1980-2009
Brown, Frank R.
2008132 Aa 2
A collection of historical booklets on the history African Americans in Battle Creek and Calhoun County, Michigan, compiled by historian Frank R. Brown. Subjects include African-American churches, education, sororities, fraternities, and social clubs, minority-owned businesses, women’s sports, and the arts. Also includes histories of Battle Creek chapters of the NAACP and the Urban League Guild.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Frank R Brown (donor no. 10077 ) in 2010.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Frank R. Brown is an historian of African-American life in Battle Creek and Calhoun County, Michigan. Brown holds a BA in history and government from Kentucky State University, and an MA from Indiana University. Brown has taught at Talladega College in the Division of Social Sciences, and in the Battle Creek Public School System. He is a past president of the Battle Creek Area Urban League Guild, and is active with the Battle Creek branch of the NAACP and the Battle Creek Historical Society. He has held several positions within his church, Mt. Zion AME, including financial secretary and historian, and was integral to the work of the church's Black Heritage Committee, which gathered research materials on the history of African Americans in Battle Creek. In 1991, Brown coordinated the effort to have Mt. Zion AME Church listed in Michigan's State Register of Historical Places.
The Frank R. Brown papers consist of histories on a range of topics related to African American cultural, civic, and commercial life in and around Battle Creek, Michigan. The materials were compiled by Frank R. Brown, some with the help of members of the Black Heritage Committee, based at Mt. Zion AME Church. The histories include brief narratives written by Brown; photocopies of clippings, newsletters, and other documents; photographs; and occasional letters to Brown and others. Subjects include general histories of African Americans in Battle Creek, churches, education, social clubs, sports, the arts, minority-owned businesses, the Battle Creek branch of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, and the celebration of the 200th anniversary of Sojourner Truth's birth. The church histories document the Fourth Episcopal District of the AME Church, the AME Church in Marshall Michigan, and a number of African-American churches in Battle Creek. Also included are histories of the Battle Creek chapter of the NAACP, the Southwestern Michigan Urban League Guild, and several Urban League programs, newsletters, and pamphlets. The histories have been arranged into three series: Black Heritage Committee Histories; "Old World Background, New World Experiences" Histories; and Miscellaneous Histories and Related Items.
Subjects:
African American churches--Michigan--Battle Creek.; African American churches--Michigan--Marshall.; African Americans--Michigan--Battle Creek.; African Americans--Michigan--Marshall.; African Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Battle Creek.; African Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Marshall.; Battle Creek Area Urban League.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Church history.; Brown, Frank R.; National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Battle Creek Club.; Marshall (Mich.)--Church history.; Washington Heights (Battle Creek, Mich.)
- Black Heritage Committee Histories 1996-2008
  - Arts, circa 2005 (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek Club of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Brief History of the Fourth Episcopal District of the Michigan Conference of the AME Church, 2006, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Brief History of 21 Black Churches in Battle Creek, 1849-1993 (Box 1)
  - Brief History of 34 Black Churches in Battle Creek, 1849-1998 (Box 1)
  - The Hamblin Community Center, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Medicine, Law, Dentistry, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Photograph Album and Brief History [of African Americans in Battle Creek and the Hamblin Community Center], circa 2008 (Box 1)
  - [Sojourner Truth] 200th Anniversary, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Women's Sports, 2006 (Box 2)
- "Old World Background, New World Experiences" Histories 2003-2005
  - African-American Clubs 2004 (Box 2)
  - African-American History in Battle Creek 1999 (Box 2)
  - African-American History in Battle Creek 2003 (Box 2)
  - African-American History in Battle Creek 2005 (Box 2)
  - Law and Government, 2003 (Box 2)
  - A Random Selection [of the History of African Americans in Battle Creek], 2003 (Box 2)
  - Sorority, Fraternity, Lodges, 2004 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Histories and Related Items 1980-2009
  - African Methodist Episcopal Church in the Village of Marshall, 1847-1906 (Box 2)
  - Battle Creek Area Urban League Programs, Newsletters, and Pamphlets 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Centennial Encyclopedia of the African Methodist Episcopal Church, 1916 (Box 2)
    (photocopy of 1916 volume)
  - Freedom, Justice and Equality: A Pictorial History of the NAACP, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Men's Sports, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Million Man March, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Minority Businesses in the 20th Century, circa 2003 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Church and Battle Creek Printed Material 1984-1999 (Box 3)
  - Neighborhoods of Washington Heights (Graves Addition), 1902-2007 (Box 3)
  - Photograph Album and Brief History of African-American Education in Battle Creek, 2009 (Box 3)
  - A Random Sample of Events of the Fourth Episcopal District and the AME Church, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Sojourner Truth, 1797-2000 (Box 3)
  - Southwestern Michigan Urban League Guild, Vol. 1, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Southwestern Michigan Urban League Guild, Vol. 2, 2006, 2 folders (Box 3)